Finding Aid for the Barbara and Willard Morgan photographs and papers LSC.2278
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Series 18: Collaborative work, 1920s-2000s
  - Subseries 18.1: Photography of Southwestern United States and Mexico, 1920s-1930s, 1954, 1965, undated
    - Photographic prints (medium), 1925-1929, undated
      - Willard Morgan with Model A Leica, and Willard Morgan Setting Up Leica Model A in Betatakin Cliff Ruin, by Barbara Morgan, 1928; Prints trimmed and mounted on 10 x 14 inch and smaller boards. (Box 325)
      - [Willard D. Morgan on Rainbow Bridge Testing Leica Camera by Barbara Morgan with Leica Camera], and Mono Lake photographs by Willard Morgan (Box 326)
      - Willard Morgan at Mono Lake with Eastman 5x7 View Camera by Barbara Morgan [photographed with Model A Leica], 1929; Prints, trimmed and mounted on 10 x 14 inch boards. (Box 327)
      - Willard at Rainbow Bridge, by Barbara Morgan, 1928; Prints, trimmed and mounted on 11 x 14 inch and smaller boards (3 prints). (Box 331)
      - Willard by Mono Lake by Barbara Morgan, 1929 (Box 339)
      - Willard on Rainbow Bridge by Barbara Morgan with Leica Model A, 1928; Contact sheet, mounted. (Box 436)
      - Mono Lake, Sunset, by Barbara Morgan, 1929; 2 prints trimmed and mounted on boards 10 x 11 inches, and 9-3/4 x 12 inches. (Box 328)
      - Mono Lake, by Willard Morgan, 1929; Prints trimmed and mounted on 10 x 12 inch and smaller boards. (Box 329)
      - Mono Lake and Mono Lake Lava Formations by Willard Morgan, 1928-1929; Prints, trimmed and mounted on 10 x 14 inch boards. (Box 330)
      - Mono Lake by Willard Morgan, 1929 (Box 339)
      - Mono Lake, and Willard Morgan Experimenting with Model A Leica in Betatakin Cliff Dwelling, 1928, undated; Prints trimmed and mounted on 12 x 15 inch boards. (Box 344)
      - [Mono Lake], unattributed, undated (Box 339)
      - Photographs by Barbara and Willard Morgan taken in the Southwest and California, 11 x 14 format prints (10 prints, loose) and prints trimmed and mounted on boards approximately 11 x 14 inch and smaller (6 prints). (Box 326)
        Most of the photographs by Willard include Barbara and those by Barbara include Willard. Locations include Canyon de Chelley, Arizona, California (Mono Lake), and Rainbow Bridge. Barbara Morgan photographs of Canyon de Chelley depict Willard hiking the canyon, at various stages of throwing a rope over a cedar log. Willard Morgan photographs of Barbara Morgan at Canyon de Chelley including Barbara in the canyon photographing Willard, and Barbara at campsite. Arizona photographs include Willard photographing dinosaur tracks in the Petrified Forest, and at campsite.
      - Portraits of Native Americans marked "from 35mm neg" (Box 326)
      - [Rainbow Bridge, and Trampas, Penitente, Cordova, New Mexico], unattributed, undated (Box 339)
      - Rainbow Bridge by Willard Morgan, 1928 (Box 347)
      - Southwest, Arizona by WDM, Barbara Morgan sketching in Arizona [BBM sitting on sideboard of car sketching cracked mud], 1928; Print, trimmed, mounted on 10-5/8 x 15 inch board. (Box 342)
      - [Trampas Penitente Cordova], undated (Box 436)
      - [Zuni], undated (Box 436)
      - [Zuni Weaver], 1929 (Box 436)
      - [Zuni Woman] by Willard Morgan, 1928 (Box 436)
    - Photographic prints (small), 1925-1929, 1954, 1965, undated
      - Barbara and Willard Morgan in the Southwest, Small negatives and prints. (Box 607, Folders 14-15)
        Includes photographs of Barbara Morgan painting in Grand Canyon and possibly Mono Lake, and Willard Morgan atop Rainbow Bridge.
        Also includes a booklet of contact sheets marked "1937 NYC publicity for Arizona paper" of a Western barbecue event.
        Locations include Grand Canyon, Rainbow Bridge, and Keet Steel Cliff Dwelling.
      - Papago (Tohono O'odham Nation) and other Southwest photographs, 8 x 10 format prints and smaller. (Box 154, Box 155, Box 156)
        Most of the images were taken in the 1920s, but there is also material from a 1954 trip to the Tohono O'odham Nation (Papago).
        Box 422, Folder 3 includes Barbara Morgan's notes for this trip.
        Some corresponding negatives can be found in Box 559.
    - Contact sheet books, circa 1920s-1930s (Box 313)
    - Contact prints and negatives, 1920s-1965, undated (bulk 1920s-1930s)
      - Arizona, California, Colorado, New Mexico and Utah (Box 545, Box 536)
        Includes Arizona: Grand Canyon, Canyon de Chelly, Papago (Tohono O'odham Nation); California: Mono Lake, Tahoe National Forest (Snag Lake), Mendocino National Forest [Yolla Bolly]; Colorado: Mesa Verde; New Mexico: Penitentes, and Bandelier National Monument (Rito de los Frijoles); and Utah: Rainbow Bridge
        Also includes a negative photographed by Willard Morgan with his Leica camera in which Barbara Morgan is sitting on a ledge, secured with rope and with a large artists' tablet on her lap, painting the Grand Canyon, 1928.
      - California and the Southwest, 1927-1929; 4 x 5 format prints and a box of color slides labeled "Calif. flight", undated. (Box 419)
        Some of these photographs include Barbara or Willard Morgan in key locations.
      - California locations and photographs filed A-Z., 5 x 7 and smaller prints. (Box 432)
        Includes Zuni sand paintings, Mono Lake and Snag Lake, Casa Adobe, Los Angeles, Bodie and Aurora ghost towns, Archery, Braille, California camp scenes, Dolls, Dogs and other animals, Echo Park night, Geysers (Healdsberg, Grant, Steam Wells, Canyon), Helena, Horses, Irrigation, Ishi, Lion Farm El Monte, Mob scenes--Aimee coming to L.A., Monolith, Mountain scenery, Oil wells, Peter the Hermit of Laurel Canyon, Mrs. Sooy, Restaurants, Reptiles, Trees (Hooker oak at Chico), Ukiah, Palm Canyon, Puppets, Weepah Gold Strike Nevada, Wind generator, Earthworms, and Unidentified.
      - California Plains and Southwest: Trampas, New Mexico, Arizona, Penitentes, Grand Canyon, 5 x 7 negatives and contact prints. (Box 537)
      - Canyon de Chelly - Willard and Barbara Morgan campsite (Box 424)
        Folder 3 also includes a greeting card with photograph of Barbara Morgan cooking at Canyon de Chelly campsite.
      - Grand Canyon, Canyon de Chelly, Northern California, Mono Lake, Red Rock Canyon, Navajo and Penitente country, 1920s-1930s; 5 x 7 and smaller prints and contact prints. (Box 420)
        Divider tabs include Grand Canyon, Leica, Misc. in Northern Calif: Aurora, petroglyphs, Indian stove, and camping, Mono Lake, Red Rock Canyon-1927 picturs: Bo and arrow, Annita and Barbara painting (Willard photography), Betatakin, Canyon de Chelly, Casa Blanca, Navajo Misc., Penitente Country: Trampas chuch, Hogan-roads, sheep-Morada, meeting place, archiectural detail, man with cross, etc., Penitente graves.
      - Grand Canyon, Rainbow Bridge, Southwest Museum, Snag Lake, Zuni paintings, and Papago, 1920s-1954; 5 x 7 format prints. (Box 421)
        Dividers include BBM Grand Canyon, Rainbow Bridge and hiking to it (15 miles)--WDM rockblimbing with rope, Southwest Museum: Casa Adobe, Barbara Morgan working, in costume, and in tub, Pueblo map, sand paintings, Snag Lake, Zuni paintings: Katchinas, bowls, shrine, New Mexico, Papago--1954: Notes, interviews, intro. letter, Prestini.
        Prestini divider is without prints.
      - Grand Canyon, Rainbow Bridge, Mono Lake, and Keet Steel Cliff Dwelling, 1940-1945, undated; Negatives. (Box 560)
        Includes Barbara Morgan painting in Grand Canyon and possibly Mono Lake, and Willard Morgan atop Rainbow Bridge.
      - Grand Canyon, Rainbow Bridge, Keet Steel Cliff Dwelling, and Western barbecue event (Box 607)
        Includes a booklet of contact sheets marked "1937 NYC publicity for Arizona paper" of a Western barbecue event.
        Also includes small prints of Barbara Morgan painting in Grand Canyon, Willard Morgan atop Rainbow Bridge, and Keet Seel Dwelling.
      - Papago (Tohono Oʼodham), Mesa Verde, 1954-1965; Negatives (35mm and 2-1/4") (Box 559)
        Photographs by Barbara Morgan of Douglas Morgan and a trip the two took together to Mesa Verde following Douglas's graduation from Colorado College, undated.
      - Sand painting, 5 x 7 and smaller contact prints. (Box 426)
      - Southwest negatives and contact prints, and notes re Papago (Box 422)
        Negatives and contact prints by Barbara and Willard Morgan of trips to the Southwest, and notes regarding the Papago (Tohono Oʼodham) Reservation, 1954.
      - Southwest slides, including Willard Morgan, 5mm slides. (Box 558)
        Includes one color slide of Willard Morgan in the Southwest.
      - Unattributed, 1933; 5 x 7 negatives and smaller (Box 560)
        Box 560 includes a small print (2-3/8" x 4") marked "Copyright 1933 by Chas. M. Brown / Mt. Dora, New Mexico / The great meteor Mar. 24, '33".
    - Photograph indexes and lists, 1928-1931 (Box 410, Folder 1)
    - Travel diary - Arizona and New Mexico, 1928 (Box 410, Folder 2)
    - Travel diary - Los Angeles to Paradise, California, 1926 (Box 410, Folder 3)
    - Travel diary - Los Angeles to Yolla Bolly, California, 1927 (Box 410, Folder 4)
    - Inter-American Visual Library project, 1929-1930 (Box 410, Folder 5)
    - Southwest Experiences project, 1968 (Box 410, Folder 6)
    - Writings by Willard Morgan, 1928-1930 (Box 436, Folders 10-11)
      Folders 10 and 11 contain written materials by Willard Morgan on the Southwest.
  - Subseries 18.2: Photography of New York City and other locations and subjects, circa 1920s-1930s
    This subseries contains photographic material from Barbara and Willard Morgan's early life and work in New York City and other locations. The photographs of New York City depict May Day, Washington Square Park, and other streets, signage, and city sights. There is also material for a photomural the Morgans made for the Manhattan office of the Scranton Lace Company. Other subjects include Chicago, the Philippines, athletics, aviation, and people such as William Jennings Bryan and Luther Burbank. Most of the photographs are credited to Willard Morgan, but some materials (such as a group of photographs of Europe) have unknown attribution. 5 x 7 photographic prints of Hollyhock House in box 429 are of unclear attribution, possibly photographed by Barbara Morgan.
    - Photographic prints (large), circa 1930 (Box 409)
    - Photographic prints (medium), circa 1930
      - Scranton, Pennsylvania Lace Factory, undated; 11 x 14 format prints. (Box 326)
    - Photographic prints (small) and contact prints, circa 1910s-1930s (Box 411, Box 426, Box 429, Folder 2)
    - Contact sheet books, 1930s-1940s (Box 313)
    - Roll film - negatives and contact sheets, 1930s (Box 214)
  - Subseries 18.3: Barnes Foundation and other art documentation, 1920s-2006; 1920s-1930s
    This subseries includes correspondence, notes, catalogs, lantern slides, negatives, and various formats of photographic prints from Barbara and Willard Morgan's business, Morgan Photographs, in which they made photographic reproductions of works of art for scholars, researchers, and educational purposes. The Morgans first began photographing works of art in the mid-1920s during their travels in the Southwestern United States, documenting paintings, sculptures, crafts, and architecture. In the early 1930s, they were hired to document the Barnes Foundation collection in Merion, Pennsylvania. The bulk of the material in this subseries relates to this project, but the subseries also includes photographic documentation of works of art from other public and private collections, such as MoMA, the Chicago Art Institute, the Detroit Institute of Arts, The Phillips Collection, and the Cleveland Museum of Art. The Barnes photographs include images of Albert Barnes with his collection, the exterior of the Foundation, and the interior, which show how some of the collection was displayed at the time. The collection has since been removed from its original location. The Barnes material also contains correspondence with Dr. Barnes, including letters that reveal Barnes' relationships with and opinions of other art institutions, and detail his research and art acquisitions.
    The Morgans' photographs of paintings in this subseries include works by Paul Cezanne, Giorgio de Chirico, El Greco, Paul Klee, Henri Matisse, Amedeo Modigliani, Pablo Picasso, Pierre-Auguste Renoir, Henri Rousseau, Vincent Van Gogh, as well as unattributed paintings organized by country of origin, including paintings from China, France, Italy, and Japan. Their photographs of sculptures include works labeled as originating from the Congo, Ivory Coast, Gabun Pahouin, Guinea, and Sudan. This subseries also includes the Morgans' photographs of architecture, ceramics, graphic arts, metalwork, tapestries, and textiles. (Box 255, Folders 4-5 contain inventories of these images with corresponding catalog numbers.)
    All 8 x 10 and smaller photographic prints are organized in accordance with the Morgans' original organizational structure, which can be viewed in their catalogs housed in Box 255, Folders 4-5.
    - Correspondence and financial documents, 1930-2006 (Box 255, Folders 1-3)
    - Catalog lists, circa 1930s (Box 255, Folders 4-5)
    - Notes, circa 1930s (Box 255, Folder 6)
    - Publicity material, 1932-1935 (Box 255, Folder 7, Box 256, Folder 1)
    - Dissertation by Christa J. Clarke dissertation: Defining Taste: Albert Barnes and the Promotion of African Art in the United States During the 1920s, 1998 (Box 256, Folder 2)
    - Thesis proposal by Tom Hussey: The Barnes Collection in Lantern Slides Photographed by Willard and Barbara Morgan, 1991 (Box 256, Folder 3)
      This item has been inscribed by Barnes to the Morgans and includes Barbara Morgan's notes.
    - The Art of Henri Matisse by Albert C. Barnes and Violette de Mazia, 1933 (Box 256, Folder 4)
    - Photographic prints (mounted), circa 1930s (Box 275, Folders 2-4)
    - Photographic prints (11 x 14 format), circa 1930s (Box 275, Folder 1)
    - Photographic prints (8 x 10 format), circa 1930s (Box 257, Box 258, Box 259, Box 260, Box 261, Box 262, Box 263, Box 264, Box 265, Box 266, Box 267, Box 268, Box 269, Box 270, Box 607)
    - Photographic prints (8 x 10 format) - Barnes Foundation exterior and interior, circa 1930s (Box 266, Folders 5-7)
    - Photographic prints (5 x 7 format), circa 1930s (Box 271, Box 272, Box 607)
    - Photographic prints (small), undated (Box 419)
      Some of these prints (4 x 5 format) are unidentified images of works of art. Also includes Southwestern United States, American Artists' Congress, and family photographs.
    - Contact prints, circa 1930s
      For negatives and prints of Richard Neutra and Frank Lloyd Wright works, see also Boxes 114, 115 and 116 (Series 14: Willard Morgan architectural photography and projects, Subseries 14.1 Richard Neutra, and Subseries 14.2: Frank Lloyd Wright.)
      - Contact prints of the Barnes Collection. (Box 273, Box 537)
      - Contact prints of works by architects Frank Lloyd Wright and Richard Neutra. (Box 273)
    - Lantern slides, circa 1930s
      - Lantern slides of the Barnes Foundation building, interior and exterior, and art works in the Barnes Collection including Braque, Chinese, Chirico, Corot, Courbet, and Cezanne. (Box 276)
      - Lantern slides of the Barnes Collection of works by Cezanne. (Box 277, Box 278)
      - Lantern slides of the Barnes Collection of works by Cezanne, Degas, El Greco, Goya, Japanese, Laurencin, Lurcat, Matisse, and Modigliani. (Box 279)
      - Lantern slides of the Barnes Collection of works by Modigliani, Pascin, Picasso, and Renoir. (Box 280)
      - Lantern slides of the Barnes Collection of works by Renoir, Rosseau, Rouault, Sienese, Soutine, Swabian, Tintoretto, Toulouse-Lautrec, Tyroll, Utrillo, and Van Gogh. (Box 281)
      - Lantern slides of the Barnes collection of works by Van Gogh, Veronese, Sculpture I-S, Ivory Coast, Kong Empire, Mudighani, Ogoue, and Sudan. (Box 282)
      - Architectural lantern slides of Grain Elevator, Neutra, Sullivan, and Wright. (Box 282)
      - Lantern slides indexed by Morgan Photography as Wright, Abbott, John Heartfield, Herbert Matter, and Nadar. (Box 283)
      - Photographic montages and journal covers by various and unidentified photographers. (Box 283)
      - Unidentified group photographs and one with Willard Morgan. (Box 283)
    - Lantern slides integrated with contact prints, circa 1930s
      - Lantern slides and contact prints of Barnes and other art documentation indexed by Morgan Photography as Bodi Bank, Tyuonyi (N.M.), Trampas Doorway, Trampas church, Trampas architecture, Early Nasca Textiles, Tiahuanaco tapestry, Peruvian textiles, Greek pottery, Peruvian pottery, Island Titicaca silver, Oaxaca, Mexico jade, Maya jade, Maya greenstone, Goya, Goya Dr., and El Greco. (Box 284)
      - Lantern slides and contact prints of Barnes and other art documentation indexed by Morgan Photography as El Greco, Ming, Laurencin, Matisse, Picasso, and Renoir. (Box 285)
      - Lantern slides and contact prints of Barnes and other art documentation indexed by Morgan Photography as Renoir; Rouault; Pueblo Indian pottery; Santo, New Mexico; Bulto, New Mexico; Navajo blanket B.F.; Navajo necklace B.F; Cezanne; Cezanne Peaches; Cezanne watercolor Man Seated. (Box 286)
      - Lantern slides and contact prints of Barnes and other art documentation indexed by Morgan Photography as Cezanne, Cezanne-Vollard, Cezanne Man With Skull, Cezanne Man Undressing, Cezanne Bathers, Chinese. (Box 287)
      - Lantern slides and contact prints of Barnes and other art documentation indexed by Morgan Photography as Carved Marble, Pre-Columbian sculpture, Onyx mask, Sculpture, Zuni, Zuni painting, Zuni altar painting, and Pueblo Indian. (Box 288)
      - Lantern slides and contact prints of Barnes and other art documentation indexed by Morgan Photography as Matisse, Matisse mural, Modigliani, Monet, Orozco mural, Pascin, Picasso. (Box 289)
    - Negatives, circa 1930s (Box 537, Box 548, Box 549, Box 607, Folder 18)
  - Subseries 18.4: Work by others and unidentified material
    This subseries contains photographs and reproductions of works by others, as well as unidentified material.
    - Photomontage periodicals - U.S.S.R. and Brazil, 1936, 1938 (Box 196, Folder 6)
    - Terrall, Robert, "Hearst is Still Alive!" in New Masses, pp. 3-7. June 13, 1939. (Box 196, Folder 7)
      p. 3: Hearst Over the People photomontage by Barbara Morgan.
    - Photographic prints (medium), undated (Box 340, Box 344, Box 367, Box 371, Box 374, Box 437, Box 438, Box 439, Box 607)
      These files cover a wide range of photographic subjects and dates. Many are undated and unattributed. Some photographs may have been taken by Barbara or Willard Morgan.
      Subjects include scientific photography; e.g., (Box 364 includes types of molds and spider leg photo-micrograph, Horace Bristol photo of "Radium Queen" in desert, and photographs by E. Teske) and Box 374 includes photographs by Joe Bodnar, solar corona and other subjects.
      The prints in Box 439 were originally housed in a box labeled "Action shots for Photo. Encyclo. WDM". (See original box cover in Folder 1).
    - Photographic prints (small) and contact prints, 1920s-1930s
      - circa 1920s-1930s, undated (Box 412, Folder 1, Box 429)
        box 429 includes 5 x 7 and smaller contact prints of radiation, Darkroom of Lee Parsons New Rochelle, and European posters.
      - circa 1940s, undated, 4 x 6-1/2 inch copy prints. (Box 430, Folders 1-2)
        photomontages by John Heartfield on WWII, Hitler, and Third Reich
      - Undated, Negatives and contact prints. (Box 429)
        Photographs by Barbara and Willard Morgan on various collaborative projects and travels: Barnes Foundation, Southwest Museum, Chief Standing Bear, Scranton Pennsylvania lace mill, J.C. Matson piloting Stearman airplane, California Plains and Southwest: Trampas New Mexico, Arizona, Penetente, Grand Canyon.
        Also includes Kim Weber: Freudmeman Home and Lovich Dress Display Room in Los Angeles; J.R. Davidson: Hi-Hat Restaurant, Satyr Book Shop, Schillings Flowers, Hite-Bilicke Office, Presman; and Willard Morgan: Inter-American Visual Library proposal and letters, early Leica photographs, and Barth + Contax.
        Also includes photographs by Edward Weston.
    - Contact sheet books, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 313)
    - Slides, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 218, Folder 1, Box 321)
    - Negatives, undated (Box 607, Folder 20)
      Box 607, folder 20 contains negatives and contact prints, mostly unidentified and unattributed. Some may be by Willard Morgan and others by Barbara Morgan. Also includes 35mm and 72mm negatives by Barbara Morgan of Hidden Valley Fresh Air Camp, and deer at Camp Anita.
      - by Barbara and Willard Morgan (Box 607, Folder 20)
        Contains negatives and contact prints, mostly unidentified and unattributed. Some may be by Willard Morgan and others by Barbara Morgan.
        Also includes 35mm and 72mm negatives by Barbara Morgan of Hidden Valley Fresh Air Camp, and deer at Camp Anita.
      - by Edward Weston, 5 x 7 negatives and contact print. (Box 537, Box 551, Box 558)
        Box 551, folder 2 contains negatives of Shell. Box 558, folder 21 contains copy negatives and contact prints of sand dunes.
      - by Moholy-Nagy, Edgerton, Heartfield, Ontwerd, and Europa Magazine cover, Copy negatives. (Box 548)
      - by Muybridge and Edgerton (photographic techniques) (Box 549)
      - by John Heartfield and Alfredo Valente, undated; 5 x 7 and smaller negatives. (Box 556)
      - Otis Art Institute students' works, undated; copy negatives. (Box 558)
    - Unidentified photographic and paper material, undated
      - Photographic prints, mostly unidentified and unattributed or by photographers other than Willard or Barbara Morgan., 5 x 7 and smaller prints. (Box 560, Box 607, Folders 13, 19)
        Box 560 includes a small print (2-3/8" x 4") marked "Copyright 1933 by Chas. M. Brown / Mt. Dora, New Mexico / The great meteor Mar. 24, 33"
        Box 607, folder 13 contains unattributed negatives of "Aquacade--rehearsals--Hotel St. George 1940".
      - Negatives and contact prints, mostly unidentified and unattributed, possibly related to Willard Morgan's publication or photo editorial work., 5 x 7 and smaller negatives, and strip film negatives, various formats. (Box 560, Box 607, Folder 20, Box 556)
        Box 560 contains unattributed negatives including 5 x 7 negatives of political cartoons sent to Willard Morgan, 2-1/4" unidentified negatives of a man and woman inside a house, and a 3 x 4" negative of a crane. Also includes a small print (2-3/8" x 4") marked "Copyright 1933 by Chas. M. Brown / Mt. Dora, New Mexico / The great meteor Mar. 24, '33".
      - Sabro Hasagawa, Otis Art Institute student work 1925, Barbara Morgan experimental and nature photographs, slides and negatives of Barbara Morgan photographic exhibitions (Box 558)
- Series 19: Family materials, circa 1850s-1990s; 1920s-1940s
  CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials are available for access. All requests to access audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  This series contains correspondence, genealogy, photography, film, and other materials related to the family life of Barbara and Willard Morgan, their sons Lloyd and Douglas, and other relatives.
  - Subseries 19.1: Barbara and Willard Morgan and family, 1919-1990s